Welcome back. My name is Mahni and I work on the prediction team at Mercedes.
お帰りなさいマニです Mercedes の予測チームで働いています
To understand what the prediction team does,
予測チームで行っていることを理解してもらいたいと思います
imagine at T-shaped intersection.
T 字路交差点を思い浮かべてみてください
You are a self-driving car that has just pulled up to the stop sign.
皆さんが自動運転車だとします ちょうど一時停止の標識のところで止まりました
You want to turn left but your sensors notice another vehicle coming from the left.
左に曲がりたいのですが センサーが別の車両が左からやってくるのに気が付きました
Now, let's pause for a moment.
ここで ちょっと止めてみます
At this point, you as a human probably know the green vehicle will do one of two things,
この時点で 人間のあなたなら緑色の車両の次の動きがわかるでしょう
either it will go straight or it will go right.
そのまま直進するか 右折するかのいずれかです
Well, let's say that at this point,
では これはどうでしょう
the green vehicle starts slowing down and moving right in the lane.
緑の車両が速度を落とし 右に動き始めました
Well, you probably know that they are
おそらく 車両は右に
turning right which means it is safe for you to go left.
曲がってくる だから あなたは左に行っても安全だということがわかるでしょう
By making a successful prediction,
正しい予測をすることで
you were able to make a decision that got you to your destination safely and efficiently.
目的地へ向けて安全で効率的な判断を下せました
And what makes prediction interesting but also
予測の面白いところであり また
challenging is that it is inherently multi-modal.
難しいところにもなるのが本質的にマルチモーダル 多様であることです
A good way of thinking about what that
どういう意味なのか
means is to think of how you would answer the question,
次の質問の答えを考えてみてください
"Where is the green car likely to be in five seconds?"
「緑色の車両は 5 秒後 どこにいる可能性が高いでしょうか」
If we try to come up with the probability distribution,
確率分布を考えてみてください
we would see that it has multiple peaks or moats.
山の部分と谷の部分が複数見えます
If the car is going straight,
車両が直進すれば
then the car is likely to be somewhere here.
大体 このあたりに来ます
But if the car turns right,
しかし もし右折したら
then it's more likely to be here.
今度は このあたりに来ます
And in general, the way we think about handling multi-modal uncertainty is
一般的に 多様性のある不確定要素の処理について考える場合にとる方法は
by maintaining some beliefs about how probable each potential mode is.
可能性のある各モードの確率でどのモードが起きるかを考えます
Initially, if we just see this green car coming from far away,
最初に この緑の車両が遠くから走ってきたのを確認している場合
those beliefs could be initialized using some prior knowledge about this intersection.
この交差点に関する以前の知識によって考えが初期化される場合があります
In this case, let's say that cars generally go straight at this intersection.
この場合 たとえば この交差点では車両は直進していくのが一般的とします
But as we continue watching the car,
しかし 車両を観察していると
we may notice that it is slowing down.
速度を落としているのに気づくかもしれません
Since this behavior is more consistent with turning right,
この動きは直進よりも右折と一貫性があるため
the probability of turning right increases.
右折の確率が高まります
And then, at the next timestep,
次の時間ステップで
we might notice that the car has already started turning
車両が既に右折し始めているのに気づくかもしれません
right which again increases the probability of turning right.
右折の確率がさらに高まります
And as we keep observing,
観察を続けることで
we continue updating our belief based on new evidence until eventually we
新しい証拠に基づいて考えを更新し続け
can predict with high certainty that the vehicle is turning right at this intersection.
最終的には高い確実性で車両が交差点で右折することを予測します
So the responsibility of the prediction module is to do the
そのため予測モジュールの役割は
following: We take as input a map of the world and data from sensor fusion
次の通りです入力として地図とセンサフュージョンからのデータを取得し
and generate as output some predictions of the future state of
出力として全車両及びその他の移動物体の
all the vehicles and other moving objects in the vicinity of our vehicle.
未来の状態の予測を生成します
Typically, these predictions are represented by a set
一般的に この予測は 2 つの点線矢印などを使って
of possible trajectories like that two dotted arrows
可能性のあるトラジェクトリーを示します 点線矢印は
emanating from the green car in this scenario and
緑の車両から出ていて トラジェクトリーに
an associated probability for each trajectory.
関連する確率を表します
Before we get into the details,
詳細に入る前に
let me explain what we are going to discuss in this lesson.
このレッスンの内容について説明しておきます
First, we'll go through a brief overview where you will learn
まず 予測の入力と出力に関する参照先について
a bit more about the inputs and outputs to prediction.
簡単に説明します
Next, we will talk about how prediction is actually done.
次に 予測が実際にどのように行われるのかについて説明します
We will discuss the two main classes of prediction techniques,
主要となる 2 種類の予測技術について説明します
model-based approaches and data-driven approaches.
モデルベースの手法とデータ駆動型の手法です
There, model-based approaches use mathematical models of motion to predict
モデルベースの手法では動きの数学モデルを使用して
trajectories and data-driven approaches rely
トラジェクトリーを予測します データ駆動型の手法では
on machine learning and examples to learn from.
学習元として機械学習および事例に依存します
Then, I will briefly walk you through how to apply
次に 厳格にデータ駆動型の手法を適用する
strictly data-driven approach for prediction called trajectory clustering.
方法について説明していきます この手法はトラジェクトリークラスタリングと呼ばれています
Then, we will dig into model-based approaches where I'll introduce
このあと モデルベースの手法について詳しく見ていきます
process models as a mathematical technique for modeling
車線変更 車両追跡など各種操作のモデリングを
various maneuvers like lane changes, vehicle following, etc.
行うための数学的手法としてプロセスモデルを紹介します
And introduce multi-modal estimators as
また マルチモーダル推論機能について説明します
an effective technique for handling the uncertainty associated with prediction,
予測に関連する不確定要素を処理する効果的な技術になります
namely, the uncertainty about which maneuver an object will do in a particular situation.
つまり 特定の状況において物体が行う動作に関する不確定要素を処理する技術です
Finally, we will dive deep into hybrid approaches
最後に ハイブリッド手法について掘り下げてみていきます
which use data and process models to predict motion
この手法はデータとプロセスのモデルを使用して
through a cycle of intense classification where we try to
緊張分類サイクルを通した動きを予測します ここでは
figure out what a driver wants to do and trajectory generation.
運転者が行おうとしていること およびトラジェクトリー生成を解明していきます
There we try to figure out how they are likely to do it.
つまり その確率をひもときます
We will end by implementing an algorithm called Naive Bayes to
最後はナイーブベイズと呼ばれるアルゴリズムを実装して
predict the motion of a car at a T-shaped intersection like the one you just saw.
先ほど見たような T 路地交差点での車両の動きを予測します
In the next few segments,
次のセグメントのいくつかでは
I'm going to ask you to do some reading about
一般的な予測モジュールで発生するデータ処理
the data processing that happens in a typical prediction module.
に関する文書に目を通してもらいます